Guide to the Manhattan Silver Mining Company Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Manhattan Silver Mining Company papers
1863-1884
WA MSS S-1303
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.75
(4 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, accounts, bills and receipts, and legal papers concerning silver mining in Lander County, Nevada.
Manhattan Silver Mining Company of Nevada
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the papers were purchased in 1957 from William P. Wreden on the William Robertson Coe Fund for Western Americana; two letterpress copybooks were purchased the following year from Wreden also on the Coe Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
MANHATTAN SILVER MINING COMPANY
Austin, Lander County, Nevada was established in 1863 following the discovery of silver ore in the area. Lander County remained prosperous until the early 1880s, when mine production decreased and the United States government abandoned the silver standard. The Manhattan Silver Mining Company of Nevada was established in Austin in 1863 with H. Augustin Taylor as president and Allen A. Curtis as agent and superintendent. The company was associated with several other mining companies in the Austin area.
Scope and Contents
The Manhattan Silver Mining Company Papers include correspondence and a variety of business papers spanning the dates 1863 to 1884. The papers document the operation of several mining companies, particularly the Manhattan Silver Mining Company of Austin, Nevada.
The correspondence, arranged chronologically in folders 1-13, provides brief descriptions of a variety of mining operations. H. Augustin Taylor's letters to Allen A. Curtis reveal the process of choosing and purchasing mining machinery. Taylor also discusses banking procedures, silver exchange rates, and investments in other mining companies. Curtis, the primary recipient of correspondence, was associated with several Austin mining firms. As agent for the Manhattan Silver Mining Company, he received letters dealing with employee relations, theft of ore from mines, planning and establishment of mines, and financial and legal matters pertaining to the operations of the mines.
The two letterpress copybooks (folders 13A-13B) retained copies of Curtis's outgoing letters from October 7, 1868 to October 2, 1870. The letters document the daily work of the mine's agent. Curtis's main correspondent was Taylor to whom he wrote constantly to report on mine operations, alterations to mills and plants, value of the bullion, financial and stock transactions, and other administrative details. Often the letters mention enclosed monthly operation reports, maps, and cash accounts, but these documents are not included in the copybook. Curtis also wrote to the company's banker in San Francisco, the Banking House of John Sime & Co. He sent "coin drafts" to Sime with orders for the banker on how to credit the accounts. In 1869 the company switched to W. C. Ralston's Bank of California. Finally, Curtis wrote to various companies in San Francisco and Sacramento for mining equipment and machine parts. Usually, the copybook only contains the cover letter for the order, so the supplies are not listed. Curtis was also responsible for paying these merchants and although the checks are not included the sum is usually stated in the letter.
Accounts, arranged alphabetically by company in folders 14-23 and Oversize (Box 2, folder 25), include financial statements from the American Mining Company, John Duncan Company, Ethan Allan Gold and Silver Mining Company, Manhattan Silver Mining Company, Mineral Hill Mining Company, Reese River Mining Company, Whitlock Union Gold and Silver Mining Company, and other unidentified organizations. The bills and receipts, chronologically arranged in folders 24-30 and the check receipt book, folder 31, complement the accounts.
Legal documents (folders 33-34) include a deed fragment, a county broker's license, an assayer's statement, a stock certificate, and two attachment forms for employees of Curtis. As a group, the legal documents are not very informative. A prospectus for "A New Amalgamator" by John T. Strauss of New York is located in folder 35.
The papers, although incomplete and unfocused, provide information on the development of mining companies in Austin, Nevada, during the nineteenth century.
Industries -- Nevada; Mineral industries -- Nevada; Silver mines and mining -- Nevada; Austin (Nev.); Lander County (Nev.); Account books -- United States; Silver miners -- Nevada; Curtis, Allen A.; Taylor, W. Augustin; Manhattan Silver Mining Company of Nevada
- Box and Folder List
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1866-67 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Correspondence, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1875-78 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1881-84 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letterpress copybook, 1868-69 Nov (Box 1, Folder 13A)
      Scope and Contents
      See: Volume 1, shelved after Box 1
    - Letterpress copybook, 1869 Dec-70 (Box 1, Folder 13B)
      See: Volume 2, shelved after Box 1
  - ACCOUNTS
    - American Mining Company, 1870, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ethan Allan Gold and Silver Mining Company, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - John W. Duncan Company, 1864-66 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Manhattan Silver Mining Company, 1865-82 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mineral Hill Mining Company, 1870-71 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Reese River Mining Company, 1863-64 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Whitlock Union Gold and Silver Mining Company, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Oversize, Box 2, folder 36
    - Accounts, miscellaneous, 1864-77, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Bills and receipts, 1863-65, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24-30)
    - Check receipt book, 1865-66 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Ledger book, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Legal documents, 1864-82 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    - Prospectus, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - OVERSIZE
    - Accounts: Whitlock Union Gold and Silver Mining Company, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 36)